REFAAT BITAR

Software Engineer

refaatbitar@gmail.com

Refaat Bitar Istanbul, Turkey O

+90 5305859283

PROFILE

I'm an experienced Full-stack Developer with 3+ years of hands-on experience. I build web applications/websites with React and Nodejs powered by Typescript and develop APIs and event-driven design services to be integrated into CRMs.

Furthermore, I have worked previously with PHP (Laravel, WordPress), Vue, and Svelte. In addition, I boosted my DevOps skills using tools such as Git, Docker, Kubernetes, and Google Cloud (Dialogflow) by following certified cloud engineers' practices.

EDUCATION

Mechatronics Engineer

2012-2017

University of Aleppo, Syria

Bachelor's Degree in Electronics/Mechatronics Engineering.

Grade: Good

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer

Jun 2020 - Present

DVCOM Technology

Istanbul – Full time (Hybrid)

Business sector: Telecommunications

- Develop REST APIs with Express (Nodejs framework).
- Responsible for connecting third-party platforms (e.g., WABA, Telegram, Twitter, SOAP web services, Ticketing and CRM systems) with xCally Motion (call center)
- Develop front-to-back web applications with React and Express.
- Automate services using Bash and/or Nodejs.
- Design and implement custom chatbot workflows.
- Maintain servers (e.g., Centos7, Debian 11, IIS) of network errors.
- Communicate with customers to produce custom analytical reports (tabular, charts).

Laravel/Frontend Developer

Jan 2020 - March 2020

Namaa Solutions

Istanbul – Full time (On-site)

Business sector: Information Technology & Services

- Develop frontend applications in Vue.
- Develop REST APIs using Laravel.

WordPress/Frontend Developer

Jan 2019 - Jan 2020

Spherical Mind

Istanbul – Full time (On-site)

Business sector: Information Technology & Services

- Develop and deliver WordPress websites from A to Z.
- Convert HTML templates to full-functional WordPress templates.
- Develop custom WordPress plugins.
- Handle SSL certificates and configure Emails in cPanel.

SELF-DEVELOPMENT

0	2019	Vocational Diploma in AutoCAD and SolidWorks.
0	2018	IELTS certificate with an overall band of 6.5.
0	2017	Graduation project on Designing and Implementation of Mechatronics System of Tracked Robot to Operate in Difficult Environments.
0	2016	Semester project on Vending Machine programming using VHDL.

PROFISSIONAL SKILLS

- Advanced command in HTML, CSS (Bootstrap, Tailwind), JavaScript (DOM, jQuery, Ejs, Handlebars.js, Dust.js, Inertia.js, Webpack, Babel)
- Advanced command in React.js (Hooks, Context API, Next).
- Advanced command of concepts in CMS, Headless CMS, E-Commerce, Forums, Blogs, REST APIs, GraphQL, i18n, APIs and User Authentication.
- Advanced command with Databases with both versions: on-premise (MySQL, MongoDB, PostgreSQL) and cloud (Firebase, Supabase).
- Advanced command of Node.js (Express, npm, Socket.io).
- Intermediate command of Networking (SSH, Routing, Firewall, NGINX).
- Intermediate command in Vue.js (Composition API, Nuxt).
- Intermediate command of PHP (Laravel, WordPress).
- Intermediate command of DevOps tools (Docker, Kubernetes) and version control with Git.

EXPERIENCE SKILLS

- Inspire and motivate the team to effective changes as required, cheerful personality, can work under pressure and meet deadlines.
- Evaluate client work scope and recommend solutions.
- Prepare and execute existing work strategies in order to increase efficiency.

SOFTWARE PROGRAM SKILLS

- Postman, FileZilla, RDP, VSCode, CLIs.
- SolidWorks, AutoCAD.
- Microsoft Office Suite (Word, Excel, PowerPoint).

LANGUAGES

Arabic: Native or bilingual proficiency

English: Full professional or C-

Turkish: Limited or A+